He was never in time for his classes... He wasn't in time for his
dinner... Then one day... he wasn't in his time at all.
Back to the Future is a adventure, comedy, science
fiction film directed by Robert Zemeckis.
Eighties teenager Marty McFly is accidentally sent back in time to 1955, inadvertently
disrupting his parents' first meeting and attracting his mother's romantic interest.
Marty must repair the damage to history by rekindling his parents' romance and - with
the help of his eccentric inventor friend Doc Brown - return to 1985.
Marty McFly, played by Michael J. Fox.
Emmett Brown, played by Christopher Lloyd.
George McFly, played by Crispin Glover.
Lorraine Baines, played by Lea Thompson.
Jennifer Parker, played by Claudia Wells.
Biff Tannen, played by Thomas F. Wilson.
Back to the Future is a 1985 American science fiction film directed by
Robert Zemeckis and written by Zemeckis and Bob Gale.
It stars Michael J.
Fox, Christopher Lloyd, Lea Thompson, Crispin Glover, and Thomas F.
Set in 1985, it follows Marty McFly (Fox), a teenager accidentally sent back to 1955 in a time-traveling DeLorean automobile built by his eccentric scientist friend Emmett "Doc" Brown (Lloyd),
where he inadvertently prevents his future parents from falling in love – threatening his own existence – and is forced to reconcile them and somehow get back to the future.
Gale and Zemeckis conceived the idea for Back to the Future in 1980.
They were desperate for a successful film after numerous collaborative failures, but the project was rejected more than forty times
by various studios because it was not considered raunchy enough to compete with the successful comedies of the era.
A development deal was secured with Universal Pictures following
Zemeckis's success directing Romancing the Stone (1984).
Fox was the first choice to portray Marty but was
unavailable; Eric Stoltz was cast instead.
Shortly after principal photography began in November 1984, Zemeckis determined Stoltz was not right for the part and made the
concessions necessary to hire Fox, including re-filming scenes already shot with Stoltz and adding $4 million to the budget.
Back to the Future was filmed in and around California and on sets at
Universal Studios, and concluded the following April.
After highly successful test screenings, the release date was brought forward to July 3, 1985,
giving the film more time in theaters during the busiest period of the theatrical year.
The change resulted in a rushed post-production
schedule and some incomplete special effects.
Nevertheless, Back to the Future was a critical and commercial success, earning
$398 million to become the highest-grossing film of 1985 worldwide.
Critics praised the story, humor, and the cast,
particularly Fox, Lloyd, Thompson, and Glover.
It received multiple award nominations and won an Academy
Award, three Saturn Awards, and a Hugo Award.
Its theme song, "The Power of Love" by Huey Lewis
and the News, was also a success.
Back to the Future has since grown in esteem and is now considered by critics and audiences to
be one of the greatest science fiction films and among the best films ever made.
In 2007, the United States Library of Congress selected it for
preservation in the National Film Registry.
The film was followed by two sequels, Back to the Future Part II
(1989) and Back to the Future Part III (1990).
Spurred by the film's dedicated fan following and effect on popular culture, Universal Studios launched a multimedia
franchise, which now includes video games, theme park rides, an animated television series, and a stage musical.
Its enduring popularity has prompted numerous books about its
production, documentaries, and commercials.
The film explores themes of flying car, race against
time, clock tower, car race, lightning.
The tone is lighthearted and thought_provoking.